<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-17T13:24:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Devesh Anand</title><subtitle>I am Devesh Anand. This is my online haven where I share my thoughts  and my work.  I write my blog from time to time.
</subtitle><author><name>Devesh Anand</name></author><entry><title type="html">Depression</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/17/depression.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Depression" /><published>2020-06-17T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/17/depression</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/17/depression.html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/depression.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Depression&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;From anime Mob Psycho 100&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 13th June, 2020, bollywood actor Sushant Singh Rajput committed suicide. He was under severe depression due to personal and professional life issues. Here he committed suicide, and suddenly everyone woke up from their dead slumber of ignorance and started talking about issues like &lt;em&gt;nepotism&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;depression&lt;/em&gt; itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might offend a lot of people, but this is the most hypocrite generation I have ever witnessed(which includes me). We live in trends. Someone men made derogatory remarks on women, and suddenly social media was flooded with, “All men are trash.” A youtuber rants on tik-tokers, and suddenly everyone becomes his bhakt(including die-hard fans of tik-tok itself) saying, “Ban tik-tok”. And now when somebody is dead(and never coming back), everyone is so much aware and conscious about mental-health issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly everyone is posting, “You can talk to me, reach out to me”, and what good will that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“momentary awareness”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; of yours will do? Maximum people are going with the flow. Now let’s say you belong to the group who genuinely cares, do you really think this &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“momentary sympathy”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; will do them(the depressed) any good? Here’s the truth: &lt;em&gt;“Nobody likes to be pitied.”&lt;/em&gt; There’s a huge difference between genuine &lt;strong&gt;care&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sympathy&lt;/strong&gt;. Ask yourself(and be honest), have you been there for people close to you when they needed you? Even if you weren’t for once, then go help your friends and family first before you try to become a &lt;em&gt;saviour&lt;/em&gt; by helping random strangers on internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And stop misusing the word &lt;strong&gt;“depression”&lt;/strong&gt;. Scoring less marks, losing a game or failing in some pursuit is not depression. Sadness? Yes, depression? Absolutely not.  &lt;br /&gt;
Remember that story &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.read.gov/aesop/043.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Shepard boy and the wolf&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? How the boy called villagers for fun, lying there was a wolf? And when there actually was, no one came and he suffered.  &lt;br /&gt;
Whenever you use the word &lt;strong&gt;depression&lt;/strong&gt; to describe your &lt;strong&gt;bad mood&lt;/strong&gt;, you leave a subconscious impact on people around. Slowly, this impact reduces the importance and meaning of this serious issue in society as a whole, and when someone is genuinely depressed, people do exactly what they shouldn’t: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Be negligent&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Some of them don’t even hesitate to mock the person, and trust me, it’s not entirely their fault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t something new to me. I lost my cousin brother due to depression. A friend of mine, who was one of the most cheerful and enthusiastic girl I had ever met, became a victim of depression. Someone very near to me said, &lt;em&gt;“Hope is a trap and a star both.”&lt;/em&gt; To be honest I am not naively optimistic(looking at the current scenario), but I believe there’s still hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The harsh reality is there will be a lot of times when there will be no one to stand with you, so learn to stand for yourself. Be strong. Be brave. As Jordan Peterson puts it, &lt;em&gt;“Life is suffering, so get your act together.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wLvd_ZbX1w0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And try not to fall for these &lt;em&gt;trends&lt;/em&gt;. Be better. I know that you can be. And act when there’s still time. Once someone is gone, you can’t bring them back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep going, never give up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devesh Anand</name></author><summary type="html">From anime Mob Psycho 100</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/depression.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/depression.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Do less, to do more</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/13/do-less-to-do-more.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do less, to do more" /><published>2020-06-13T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-13T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/13/do-less-to-do-more</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/13/do-less-to-do-more.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/do less to do more/time-fading.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;do less to do more&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me take you through the routine of our forefathers. Waking up early, cleaning their teeth, pooping, bathing, then having some breakfast with family and then finally going to work. Working the whole day and the coming back to the house. Having food, spending time talking to loved ones, doing some house chores and finally going to sleep. Once in a while they went to watch theatre, movie or puppet-show(depending on the era they lived in), which took place at a specific period of every month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s talk about today’s life. Waking up, checking the phone, getting ready, sitting for breakfast, checking the phone(or watching tv), finding something interesting and adding it to your &lt;em&gt;“to do list”&lt;/em&gt;. The list goes on and on and on…  &lt;br /&gt;
One year forward, you look at the list and realise you hardly completed any tasks in it, but still you keep on adding more goals(and tasks) to it. You want to be a doctor(or engineer), writer, guitarist, gamer, activist and can’t afford to miss the upcoming series, because FOMO. Eventually you become overwhelmed with all the expectation you have with yourself. You realise you are nowhere near to achieving any of your goals. Honestly, this was inevitable. You can’t do everything, and this is one really important issue that is often neglected(and ignored).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common(and deadly misconception) today is: &lt;em&gt;“More productivity means more work”&lt;/em&gt;. Well the more one works, the more productive one will be, right? Wrong. It’s a trap. Productivity is about efficient work, not &lt;em&gt;“more”&lt;/em&gt; work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;80/20 rule (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Pareto principle&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) :&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/do less to do more/Pareto-Principle.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pareto principle&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Pareto principle&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“80% of results are based on 20% of your input”. The numbers may go up and down a little bit, but what really matters is the fact that a small proportion of work efforts result in maximum results. This principle given by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vilfredo_Pareto&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
Vilfredo Pareto&lt;/a&gt; was initially a economic principle, but research proved that it can be applied to a wide variety of fields, which includes productivity. You can apply this rule almost everywhere. From studies, to daily house chores, or even your to-do list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your day to day life, you’ll notice this principle almost everywhere. Of all the entertainment apps, you use only 20%. You call 20% of the people frequently whom you know. Of all the clothes you have, you wear 20% more frequently. 20% of your social media followers will engage regularly with what you post. 20% of the artists and entrepreneurs actually make it through the grind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that kid from school who didn’t pay much attention to studies, and yet his scores were above average in every test? And whenever you asked them &lt;em&gt;“their secret”&lt;/em&gt;, they acted like genius. A perfect example of 80/20 rule(and show-off). Here’s what they did: They payed utmost attention to the most important 20% of the syllabus, which helped them in scoring efficiently. I can vouch for this example as I have been there, done that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now how to use this principle? Start by being impartial. Ask yourself which tasks are the most important, and prioritize them. Soon you’ll notice a pattern that these &lt;em&gt;“most important”&lt;/em&gt; tasks will roughly sum up to 20% of the total list. The key is not to fall for temptation of doing everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Fear Of Missing Out (FOMO) :&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/do less to do more/FOMO.png&quot; alt=&quot;Fear Of Missing Out&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Fear Of Missing Out&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What were the last 3 webseries/shows/anime you watched? Ask yourself genuinely whether you actually were interested in them, or was it because of the fact that everyone else was watching it. A lot of times you might have done things just because you wanted to be part of some conversation, conversation that will perhaps never matter in your life again. Constantly surfing you social-media feeds so that you don’t miss someone’s status updates. This constant anxiety(or fear) of being connected with what others are doing is toxic, costs your mental peace in long term and ultimately affects your productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest trends feed on what I call, &lt;strong&gt;“The collective anxiety”&lt;/strong&gt;. You’re not alone. There are millions more struggling with FOMO and meaningless trends(or challenges) catch fire online due to this reason. Even big corporations use your weakness in their marketing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fear_of_missing_out#Marketing_technique&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;strategies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People today live in a subconscious &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fear Of Missing Out&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. There’s a very thin line between choosing for yourself and choosing because of someone else. Well of course others might recommend you cool and enlightening stuff, but not every time. You are not missing out much by not seeing someone’s social media feed, or by being a part of latest trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solution? Understand that you are not missing out. Keep check of your social media usage. If something won’t be of much use in future, do yourself a favour by not doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Paradox Of Choices :&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/do less to do more/steveattire.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;steve jobs attire&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Steve Jobs in same attire at different keynotes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Unless you’re from a different world(or live in a cave), chances are you would’ve heard of Steve Jobs. Here’s an interesting observation. If you check out any of his interview or keynote, you’ll see him wearing similar black shirt and blue jeans ever single time. No, he didn’t wear the same clothes again and again everyday, instead he had a wardrobe full of same attire. He followed a principle called &lt;em&gt;“Standard Operating Procedures”&lt;/em&gt;(SOP in short form). His point was, people waste time everyday choosing what to wear, and since his time was precious, he decided to fix this issue. Even Mark Zuckerberg was inspired by this and started wearing grey shirt everyday at work. The point is, they boiled down the number of choices they had to made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a psychological hack that might come in handy. Imagine I ask you out for a dinner. If I genuinely want you to make the choice of restaurant, I would give you a few restaurants to choose from.  &lt;br /&gt;
But if I want to make the choice of restaurant(not you) without sounding bossy, I will simply remove the choices from the question, leading you to unlimited choices to choose from, and most likely, you will agree with the restaurant I suggest. Basically the more the number of choices you have, the more difficult it will be to choose from. So boil down the number of things to do to as minimum as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first two paragraphs, I talked about the routine of our forefathers and the current generation. Our forefathers didn’t have much options to choose from. Even if they had, they would religiously boil them down to a few. Today, we have unlimited options. We jump into activities everyday that do nothing except devouring our precious time. Why? Because we don’t choose wisely what we should do, and what not. Zakir Khan puts it in a beautiful way in his podcast(in hindi) &lt;a href=&quot;https://gaana.com/song/ep-11-winning-is-not-important&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“Umeed- Episode 11”&lt;/a&gt;:  &lt;br /&gt;
“You need to choose your own battles”, and not every battle is worth fighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this era of unlimited things to do, invest your time wisely in pursuits that matter. Focus on things that actually matter, not the ones you fool yourself to &lt;em&gt;“think”&lt;/em&gt; matter.&lt;br /&gt;
Do less, accomplish more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep going, never give up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devesh Anand</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog//do%20less%20to%20do%20more/time-fading.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog//do%20less%20to%20do%20more/time-fading.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fear</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/28/fear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fear" /><published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/28/fear</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/28/fear.html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/fear.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fear&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Illustration by Aaron Blanco&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
A word that can’t be aptly defined in any dictionary or book. It’s an emotion, an emotion powerful enough to blur logic and rational decision making. The one who has felt it, is the one who knows. Funny thing is, it’s a product of our own imaginations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try remembering the things you were scared of as a kid. Things that terrified you. Think, and you will soon find that most of them were just imaginary. Personally, like most other small children, I was scared to death by ghosts and darkness. Now, I know darkness is absence of light or photons(yes, I took science). And as far as it about ghosts, now I know they aren’t real(OK, maybe they are).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fear is more like your first crush. You don’t know much about the person, yet you give them too much importance and respect in your head. Without knowing much, you end up thinking that they are your &lt;em&gt;“ideal partner”&lt;/em&gt;. They seem so genuine in your mind, they’re perfect.  &lt;br /&gt;
Now see fear from the same perspective. Without knowing exactly what it is, you make too big a deal of it in your mind. You make it the &lt;em&gt;“ideal thing”&lt;/em&gt; that can kill you or destroy you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that mad stray dog? The dog that chased you, and you thought you were going to get bit? Well, that dog is fear. The moment you start running, it starts to chase you, but that’s the point! Running away was actually the reason you caused the dog to chase you. It’s a mistake we all make. Actually it’s more of a necessary step that confirms whether our fear is real or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your fears are genuine. You might be scared to lose some people. Imagining a life without them might be terrifying, but does it make fear a bad thing? No. It’s actually the most important instinct we humans ever had. It’s the fear of losing something that makes you realise how valuable the thing or the person is, and this realization gives you a reason to continue fighting for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong. Some people want to &lt;em&gt;“eradicate fear”&lt;/em&gt; from their lives, which is actually a tremendously stupid idea.  &lt;br /&gt;
Imagine not being afraid of anything. You get a little frustrated over some issue, start getting suicidal thoughts and since you lack fear, you successfully attempt suicide! Now imagine another scenario where you come over your frustration and perform better next time. Sounds better, right?  &lt;br /&gt;
In simple words, fear prevents you from killing yourself and further pushes you to evolve. The only reason you are alive today is because your ancestors survived the harshness of the world, and they survived because fear kept them away from doing stupid things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s a warning too: A lot of your fears are &lt;em&gt;“meaningless”&lt;/em&gt;. Fears, that are not actually yours, but have been incorporated in you through outside agents.  &lt;br /&gt;
There’s a line from poem &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.desiderata.com/desiderata.html&quot;&gt;Desiderata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nurture strength of spirit to shield you in sudden misfortune.  &lt;br /&gt;
But do not distress yourself with dark imaginings.  &lt;br /&gt;
Many fears are born of fatigue and loneliness.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, it’s absolutely fine to be scared, but being scared of &lt;em&gt;“meaningless”&lt;/em&gt; things? It’ll be a wastage of your precious energy and mental peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember my english teacher, Mr. David once said in class, “या तो मौज में, या तो ख़ौफ़ में”(meaning you do something either out of fun, or fear). Fear is a force, and force can be used both for constructive and destructive purposes. These words from Jordan B. Peterson describes it perfectly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You want to get your fear behind you, where it’s pushing you forward, instead of in front of you, where it’s stopping you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; - Jordan B. Peterson &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch this fantastic video in which Jordan B. Peterson explains how to get motivated by fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1W9bGi5Yc1c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fears are part of life. Accept it. NEVER try to be &lt;em&gt;“less afraid”&lt;/em&gt;, instead try to be braver because you never get rid of your fears, you just learn to live above them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep going, never give up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devesh Anand</name></author><summary type="html">Illustration by Aaron Blanco</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/fear.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/fear.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Problems</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/03/problems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Problems" /><published>2020-05-03T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/03/problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/03/problems.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/problem.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;problems&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Set&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
A chapter in math. Its basically a bunch of similar objects, stacked together. Comedians have sets of jokes, a student have set of assignments and we all humans have sets(not set) of problems. It doesn’t really matter whether one is rich or poor, successful or struggling, old or young, there are problems in everyone’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poor people struggle to fulfill their daily needs. Once in a while they are forced by circumstances to skip a meal. They don’t have enough resources to afford proper education, shelter and even clothing. These are third world problems. Then on the other side of the spectrum, there are people who have everything. They have money, status and a freedom to have a lifestyle they want, and yet they have problems. They might have deteriorating health, relationship issues or they might be struggling with some bad habits. They might be drug addicts. They might have undealt psychological trauma. Basically these problems fall under the category of &lt;em&gt;‘first world problems’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A grownup has to make sure they have enough money in bank account to pay the bills in upcoming month. That’s a problem for them. A kid, whose toy is broken also has a serious problem. A student with a deadline to submit an assignment has a problem. A &lt;em&gt;maggi-lover’s&lt;/em&gt; stock runs out, that’s a problem too. Point is, the world is a jar full of problems up to the very top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Our world runs on hope.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Nonsense! Our world runs on problems. The economy doesn’t depend on cash flow, it depends on the constant flow of problems: unsolved ones incoming, solved ones outgoing. The amount of money a person makes is directly proportional to their problem-solving skills. Actually every skill you have, solves a problem. If it doesn’t, it’s not a skill, it’s a hobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might sound controversial: many great men are experts at ‘creating’ a problem, and then solving it to gain influence. And no, no reference to the current government scenario here(ok maybe a little). Current social media aren’t good enough, so have tik-tok. You already don’t look good enough, have fairness cream. You are not successful enough, watch my shitty motivational videos to be successful. And the biggest scam of this century, you’re not happy enough, go find happiness. This business of ‘problems’ is dark, destructive and unethical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being stubborn wont help. Or, being a egoist won’t help. 
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ego is the enemy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, an important stoic lesson that is evergreen. Your ego might tempt you, even fool you in thinking that either your simple problems are too big, or complex problems are too small to pay attention. You will face situations in life(for sure), when you’ll be in utter chaos. In those times, taking complete responsibility is the best option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t control your destiny, you control your choices. Now being a human, it’s natural to make choices that will make you fall in problems. The point I’m trying to make is, take responsibility. No matter how badly you believe that someone else is responsible, the truth is, at some point, it was your choice that led you to the point where you are right now. And remember, the first step to solve a problem is to accept that there is a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is full of shit, both in form of real shit and shitty people. I consciously never acknowledged it but maybe my subconscious mind knew it right from my childhood days. Maybe that’s why I have a principle- &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Keep things simple&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Before you go out thinking yourself a &lt;em&gt;‘messiah’&lt;/em&gt; who’ll solve the issues of world, first solve your own problems. I like how Jordan B. Peterson puts it, “Get your life together.” He has a simple rule: start by cleaning your room. If you can’t have your own life in order, then maybe the idea of going out and saving the world right now, is not a wise one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blaming &lt;em&gt;‘the system’&lt;/em&gt; won’t help. It’s a waste of time. &lt;em&gt;The system&lt;/em&gt; has already been built. It has been there since a long time. There were people before you(and will be in the future) with problems even bigger than your imagination, who made it to the very top going through the same &lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt; you blame. So stop whining, and accept the problems you have. That’s half battle won. Then do rigorous, unbiased analysis of the issues, and I’m sure you’ll come up with solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep going, never give up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devesh Anand</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/problem.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/problem.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">You are a slave</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/28/you-are-a-slave.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You are a slave" /><published>2020-04-28T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/28/you-are-a-slave</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/28/you-are-a-slave.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/slave.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;slavery&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are a slave. You might be thinking what nonsense! It’s ok, that’s a normal human response to anything to which your belief system disagrees to.  &lt;br /&gt;
I clearly want to state I am not going to explore this topic from a symbolic(or existential) perspective, i.e, I wouldn’t be talking about the fact that we are slaves to time, God, or any other phenomena, that is not under our control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will explore the slavery you have put yourself into yourself. Knowingly or unknowingly, that’s another issue. Read the post completely, or simply don’t read at all. Half read post will do you more harm than good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re reading this in the 21st century, chances are you are already a victim of &lt;em&gt;‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/intl/blog/mind-change/201507/digital-dementia&quot;&gt;Digital Dementia&lt;/a&gt;’&lt;/em&gt;, in simple words, you are a slave to technology. Ever felt that you’re kind of lost and dizzy after a long session of screen time? Well, that is a clear symptom of dementia. And yes, I know there’s a difference between relying on something, and being a slave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so it started like it starts every time. In America, British settlers came, the Red Indians didn’t pay much attention, and boom, the land was no more theirs. Something same happened in India. Britishers came for trade, and we welcomed them with open arms. Trade was beneficial for sure, but we failed to keep their actions and desires in check. Result? 200 years of slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case with technology has been quite similar. Tech came in 1990s for the masses, suddenly erupted like wild fire in 2000s and was now a part of our lives. In this decade, we became heavily reliant on technology. Same mistake once again. We lost the track of when we became followers of technology, instead of it being the other way round. The time frame in which tech became mainstream is just too short, it is 15-20 years, and as expected, we humans couldn’t see the harmful impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When social media addiction first came under public attention, that was probably the first time the human society was alarmed. Then came an endless number of serious addictions associated with technology. Porn addiction, gaming addiction and now, addiction to video content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what’s really interesting? Many people simply deny that they are addicted. They know they show every possible symptom, yet they fool themselves saying, ”Oh, I can keep down the phone whenever I want to!” Really? Then why is there such an unease when you can’t find your gadget near you for sometime? Why can’t you stay away from social media for a few days?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you don’t want to. In better terms, your brain doesn’t allow you to. The need to secrete the feel good hormone surpasses logic and rational thinking. The thing about the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/dopamine-addiction&quot;&gt;‘feel good hormone’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; dopamine is that it is the same hormone that makes a sane alcohol consumer alcoholic, a person (just )trying drugs a drug addict and a smoker, a chain smoker(not the band). Honestly, I personally struggle from the problem of addiction from time to time. The games! God they are just so mind blowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a shocking news: Big corporations around the world are making billions of dollars out of your bad habit of addiction. The fact that you have become a slave to technology is the biggest reason why world’s top 5 corporations(with valuation over $600 billion each) are from tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s do some analysis about how is it harming you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s affecting your mental health.&lt;/strong&gt; Addiction of any sort is directly correlated to increase in anxiety, stress and sleep issues.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are lagging behind.&lt;/strong&gt; Your time is limited. 24 hours a day. That’s the time everyone has. You can either pursue your goals in that, or can waste it. Wasting too much time on things that aren’t helpful will naturally result into lesser time for necessary stuff, ultimately you lag behind.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It affects your relationships.&lt;/strong&gt; Whether it’s family, friends or your romantic partner. No one remains unaffected. You are a node in a huge network. If one node malfunctions, all nodes connected to it will naturally be affected.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It affects your physical health too. I don’t think I need to explain how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, it will kill you before your normal expiry date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another slavery is something I’m dead sure you are a victim of. It’s food. Did you know that &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2017/aug/25/is-sugar-really-as-addictive-as-cocaine-scientists-row-over-effect-on-body-and-brain&quot;&gt;sugar can be more addictive than cocaine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;? Chances are, you didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a mind blowing fact. A person having a protein rich breakfast will have higher chances of being agreeable, even going as far as to accept an unfair offer presented to them. Sounds funny, right? But it’s serious. This is just one of the thousands of ways your mind, habits and ultimately life can be affected just by giving you a specific kind of diet, without any added drugs or chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you might have read again and again that junk/fast food is bad for health, and like most people, your mindset would be that it causes obesity, cholesterol and heart diseases, basically ‘physical problems’, but these foods have a far serious impact on your mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They make you a junkie.&lt;/strong&gt; Your taste-buds give you a pleasing sensation when you eat something. Basically, your brain secretes &lt;em&gt;dopamine&lt;/em&gt;, which we discussed above.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They mess with your &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circadian_rhythm&quot;&gt;circadian rhythm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They affect your productivity.&lt;/strong&gt; Unhealthy diet impacts your circadian rhythm negatively, thus affecting your productivity. How? Not going to explain. Go read &lt;em&gt;circadian rhythm&lt;/em&gt; through above link.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to understand that your mind and body coexist. One’s health affects the other’s. Ever wondered why people suffering from depression become really thin(or fat)? Well, you know now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See, the thing is, you are a slave of your own desires(in a deep sense), and the reality is, you can get out of this slavery for sure, but it’ll be hard. Your brain will eventually trick you, deceive you or even force you to continue your unproductive(and bad) habits, but with proper strategy and persistence, you shall get over this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a fantastic solution to your problem. To successfully deal with the problem, I advise you to take the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vl-44jDYDJQ&quot;&gt;dopamine fast&lt;/a&gt;. The video from improvement pill describes the &lt;strong&gt;dopamine fast&lt;/strong&gt; in an outstanding manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep going, never give up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devesh Anand</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/slave.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/slave.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>